<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the nature and end of repentance shadowed in the ministerie of Iohn the Baptist. Preached the Sunday afore Lent. 1613.</title>
            <author>Case, William, 1584 or 5-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107898</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843590</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1373:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the nature and end of repentance shadowed in the ministerie of Iohn the Baptist. Preached the Sunday afore Lent. 1613.</title>
                  <author>Case, William, 1584 or 5-1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Edmund Weauer, and are to sould at the great south-dore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Case.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>John, --  the Baptist, Saint --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8333:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8333:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF THE NATVRE AND END OF <hi>Repentance:</hi> Shadowed in the Miniſterie of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached the Sunday afore <hi>Lent.</hi> 1613.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN 3.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto thee, except that a man be borne of water and the Spirit, hee cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Edmund Weauer,</hi> and are to ſould at the great South-dore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8333:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8333:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God THOMAS Lord Biſhop Elect of CHESTER, my very good LORD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Reuerend Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing heretofore moued for ſome conſiderations to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this Sermon: I remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſomewhat doubtfull in the Dedication there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vntill the newes of your Lordſhips aduancement quickly ſetled my reſolution. For where better could I haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plor'd Patronage, then where both eminent au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Place, as alſo your Lordſhips par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular fauour towards me, ſeemed no leſſe enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedly to inuite by loue, then compell by dutie? For which reſpect I haue now preſumed vpon your Lordſhips acceptance, trusting the rather to
<pb facs="tcp:8333:3"/>obtaine pardon for this my bold intruſion, and alſo indulgent cenſure of theſe my vnworthy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, preſented to your learned view as cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging the goodneſſe of your Lordſhips diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and freely offered courteſie, guiltie of this my attempt, and a chiefe cauſe hereof.</p>
            <p>The Lord God guide and aſsiſt your Lordſhip with the bleſſed directions of his moſt holy ſpirit, in the diſcharge of your high calling in this life, and in the life to come giue you the reward of immortalitie and euerlaſting glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all duetie to be commanded WILLIAM CASE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8333:3"/>
            <head>OF THE NATVRE AND END OF RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: ſhadowed in the <hi>Miniſterie</hi> of IOHN the BAPTIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN 1. Ver. 31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore am I come, Baptizing with Water.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He life of a Chriſtian in this world is a medlie, conſiſting of much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie, a continuall entercourſe of changeable ſucceſſion.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.2. &amp;c.</note> For there is a time to be borne (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to plucke vp; a time to kill, and a time to heale; a time to breake downe, and a time to build vp. A time to weepe, and a time to laugh; a time to daunce, and a time to mourne. <hi>Sic tristia ſecundis ſecunda triſtibus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudo acerba ſortis temperat.</hi> So wiſe is the euer admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Creatour in all his workes (ſaith one) as to temper
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8333:4"/>the actions of the life of man with ſuch proportion and counterpoyſe, that no proſperitie ſhall be without his ſucceeding inconuenience, no aduerſitie without his comfort; to chaſe out of mans minde ſecuritie and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, the onely enemies of all wiſe and vertuous cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. That time (beloued) is but a ſmall whiles paſt, when there was nothing heard in your gates but the voice of ioy and gladneſſe, of mirth and ſolace; and that, vpon ſo good a cauſe, as a better the world was neuer made partaker of, the memorie of the bleſſed Incarnation of the worlds Redeemer. But now leaſt the proud heart of man ſhould be exalted aboue meaſure, and puffed vp through aboundance of conſolations: Behold, there is a contrary occaſion, of a contrary affection, the ſinne of man to counteruaile the grace of God; that as afore we haue had cauſe of reioycing and feaſting; ſo now the time approacheth and is at hand, wherein we haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitation to lamenting and faſting. So that hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready celebrated with mirth and great ioy the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Chriſts comming into the world; it remaines in the next place that now by ſorrow and repentance we prepare for his comming vnto vs. For it is the ſame path which our Euangeliſt hath trodden out vnto vs in this Chapter. Wherein after he had in the beginning thereof Diuinely propoſed the comming of that light into the world, which the world being ſhut vp in blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was not able to comprehend: in the next place, immediately he proceedeth vnto the Miniſterie of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> the Miniſterie of humiliation and repentance, the better to prepare the ſoules of men to entertaine that heauenly gueſt, for which in that eſtate they naturally were in, they were moſt vnfit. For indeede it was the meere ſcope of <hi>Iohns</hi> Miniſterie to prepare thoſe by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which by the miniſterie of Chriſt were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be ſanctified by faith and other graces of the ſpirit: Which thing as the Baptiſt vpon occaſion diuers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8333:4"/>times in ſundrie paſſages of this Chapter ſpecifieth and witneſſeth of himſelfe; ſo ſpecially in this place, vpon the ſight of Ieſus comming towards him, as you may ſee in the coherence: he inferreth this ſame teſtimonie of his owne Miniſterie, in the words which I haue now read vnto you, <hi>[Therefore am I come, Baptizing with water,]</hi> intimating vnto his Diſciples two things, which are now alſo of vs to be conſidered. His Office; and the end of his office: His Office and Miniſterie in theſe words, <hi>[I am come, Baptizing with water,]</hi> and the end of his Office implied and included in the illatiue particle <hi>[therefore,]</hi> that is to ſay <hi>[that Chriſt might be made manifeſt vnto Iſrael, therefore am I come, Baptizing with water.]</hi> So that in theſe words now read vnto you, I haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion giuen to ſpeake of the Office of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> in a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold reſpect. Firſt, of the poſitiue &amp; abſolute nature of it, what it is, and the parts thereof: And ſecondly, of the relatiue nature of it, how of it ſelfe it is but a rudiment, and a preparatiue to a further degree of perfection; and yet notwithſtanding ſo neceſſarie, that the other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it is likewiſe imperfect, The abſolute nature of his office and miniſterie, is here noted out vnto vs to be the <hi>[Baptiſme of water;]</hi> which as it is many times taken figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely in the Scriptures in diuers ſignifications, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this place by a <hi>ſynechadoche.</hi> it is taken for the whole courſe of <hi>Iohns</hi> calling and Miniſterie. Whereof thereare two parts: The ſubſtance of it, which was the doctrine of repentance for the remiſſion of ſinnes: And ſecondly, the ceremonie of it, or the ſeale of that doctrine, the outward adminiſtration of the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake therefore properly of the ſubſtance of <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme, is to ſpeake of Repentance, which hee Preached onely in the whole courſe of his Miniſterie. Now what repentance is, where ſhould we better learne then of him, who was the Preacher of Repentance? of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8333:5"/>the Baptiſt himſelfe, the precurſor of the worlds Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who teacheth it firſt by Precept; ſecondly, by the parts of it; and thirdly by Patterne in his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. By Precept ſhewing that it muſt be: by parts of it, ſhewing what it muſt be, and by patterne ſhewing how it muſt be practiſed of all that hope to reape benefit by the incarnation of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>And firſt he taught it by precept in the third of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, ver.</hi> 3. When he ſaith, <hi>Repent, for the Kingdome of God is at hand.</hi> Which ſentence ſeemeth not ſo much a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept impoſing by commandment a duety neceſſarily to be performed, as a counſell, becauſe a reaſon is annexed: for then he might haue ſaid, <hi>Repent,</hi> and no more: Neither doth it onely ſeeme to be a counſell, but rather a louing perſwaſion, becauſe the reaſon is ſo amiable and louely, for it might haue beene otherwiſe propoſed as it was in another place by our Sauiour, <hi>Repent leaſt yee periſh:</hi> But here it is, <hi>Repent, for the kingdome of God is at hand:</hi> as if he ſhould haue ſaid, The time was when as the hardneſſe of mens hearts had lockt vp and faſt barr'd the doores of grace, ſo that then there was neither hope of expecting, nor meanes of obtaining mercie or fauour at the hands of God. But behold! now (ſuch is the goodneſſe of God) the time approacheth and is nigh at hand, when as the gates of the kingdome of heauen ſhall be ſet wide open; and therefore now; if euer, is the acceptable time; now is the day of Saluation: <hi>to day if yee will heare his voice har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den not your hearts, &amp;.</hi> A moſt forceable perſwaſion and ſweete allurement, agreeable to the glad tydings of the Goſpell: yea, euen to the <hi>beginning of the Goſpell</hi> (as Saint <hi>Marke</hi> cals it) the Doctrine of Repentance: which albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it for the moſt part it be a doctrine of ſharpe rebukes and ſeuere diſcipline, yet is it mixed with ſuch gracious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and incitations of encouragement to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of it, as driues away all thoughts and doubts of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8333:5"/>danger or deſpaire, howſoeuer it be branded by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Libertines with an imputation of crueltie, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſperate horrour and diſtraction in the ſoule and conſciences of man. For although the duetie of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance impoſed, be very troubleſome &amp; harſh vnto fleſh and blood, yet is the end of our repentance ſo full of comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſucceſſe as doth alleuiate all forrowes and make the yoake eaſie and the burden light. And therefore if Chriſt doe call vs, though it be with <hi>Peter</hi> to walke vpon the Sea, yet let vs goe vnto him; and though mighty windes, whether outward croſſes of the world, or inward terrors of conſcience, through our infirmitie &amp; infidelity may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright &amp; wel-nigh ouerwhelme vs; yet if, when we begin to ſinke, we can but ſay with <hi>Peter, Maiſter ſaue vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 14.29.</note> our Lord Ieſus will ſtretch forth his hand and catch vs, But if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commandments can force vs, nor reaſons perſwade vs, nor louing allurements draw vs to the vndertaking of this happy (though heauie) courſe of Repentance: it ſhall not be our <hi>pleading that Abraham is our Father,</hi> that ſhall helpe vs;<note place="margin">Math. 3.9.10.</note> for <hi>God is able euen of theſe ſtonges to raiſe vp children vnto Abraham. Now alſo is the axe laid vnto the roote of the tree, and therefore euery tree that bringoth not foorth good fruite, ſhall be hewne downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> Implying this much, that they who will not kiſſe the Sonne, as friendly ſubiecta, and be ruled by his Scepter now in his kingdome; ſhall hereafter be ſubdued by the Sonne, as his enemies, and bruiſed in peeces with his iron rodde in the day of his wrathfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the reward is ſo great, which is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to repentance, euen the kingdome of heauen; and on the other ſide the puniſhment ſo great if we doe not repent as thereby to incurre the danger of euerlaſting fire: it will haply ſo fall out, that as <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>Iohn</hi> gladly vntill he was rebuked for his inceſtuous marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; ſo many it may be will willingly entertaine with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8333:6"/>the doctrine of <hi>Iohn,</hi> vntill their deareſt ſinnes be reproued; and then, rather then they will be deuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from that adulterous broode, which with ſo great liking and delight they nouriſh, as chaſte ſpouſes, in their boſomes; rather (I ſay) then they will ſuffer rebuke for them, or be drawne to forſake them, they will not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeke to contemne the calling and diſgrace the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but euen if they could alſo take the heads of thoſe Miniſters that ſhall ſo boldely cenſure and ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto themſelues. And therefore wee cannot well tell what we ſhall be, vntill we know what repentance is in the parts of it.</p>
            <p>And that the Baptiſt teacheth in the third of <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpell, and the fifth verſe, diſtinguiſhing the ſame into foure ſeuerall ſpeciall parts; compriſing therein all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular braunches that reſpectiuely may be referred thereunto. When he ſaith, <hi>Euery valley ſhall be filled and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mountaine and hill ſhall be brought low,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>and the crooked things ſhall be made ſtraight, and the rough waies ſhall be made ſmooth, and ſo all fleſh ſhall ſee the ſaluation of God:</hi> Wherein he doth not onely intimate and inferre the end and fruit of Repentance in generall, that it is a propertie thereof to pull thoſe ſcales of ignorance and ſenſualitie from off the eyes of our vnderſtanding, without which we could not otherwiſe apprehend and ſee the ſaluation by Chriſt offered vnto vs: but alſo by an allegorie doth manifeſtly declare wherein true repentance doth conſiſt, and doth likewiſe particular the parts thereof. For whereas the nature of repentance is nothing elſe but a mortification of all ſinne, and a generall amendment of life: there is no irregularitie whatſoeuer whereby the ſoule of man is diuerted from the righteous rule of Gods law, but the reformation thereof may be reduced vnto one of theſe foure heads: either in filling the vallies, or in leuelling the mountaines; in making ſtraight the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or the rough in being made ſmooth: for the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8333:6"/>are filled, when as our <hi>affections are raiſed from the things on the earth, and are ſet on thoſe things that are aboue. Col.</hi> 3.2. The mountaines are brought low, when the proud thoughts of man are <hi>captiuated to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. The crooked things are made ſtraight when the vnrighteouſneſſe of our actions are brought within ſuch compaſſe as that we <hi>doe not otherwiſe vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers then we would haue others to doe vnto vs, Mat.</hi> 7.12. And laſtly, the rough things become ſmooth when as we willingly take the <hi>yoake of Chriſt vpon vs. and learne of him to be lowlie and meeke. Math.</hi> 11.29. For by Valleyes, Mountaines and crooked waies and rough, (as farre as I can conceiue there of) can be vnderſtood nothing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the baſe earthlineſſe of our affections, the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling pride of our hearts, the vniuſt iniquitie of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the peruerſe frowardneſſe of our wils. Theſe foure containing within them the whole diſorder of the frame of mans nature. For inaſmuch as the direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit of grace hath forſaken vs, becauſe firſt we had forſaken him: there is now no better deſires in the heart of man; but firſt an eager purſuite and delight which he hath onely in the things of this world. Secondly, a vaine-glorious pride and boaſting which he taketh in them hen he hath them. Thirdly, the meanes whereby he doth attaine vnto them are indirect and iniurious: And laſtly, if he fade or be croſt in the proſecution of them, his paſſions are troubleſome and boyſterous. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which ſoure vices, all other are comprehended; as all graces are vnder theſe foure, that are directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite vnto them, for indeede they are <hi>ex diametro,</hi> directly oppoſed vnto thoſe foure generall diuine graces, from whence all other doe ſpring. <hi>Faith, Obedience, Loue</hi> and <hi>Patience.</hi> Our earthly and baſe affections being ſo faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the pleaſures and delights of this world, that our faith cannot be ſtedfaſt concerning the pleaſures of a better world; and ſo we ſinne againſt our Lord and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8333:7"/>Sauiour. Secondly, our pride and high conceit of our ſelues is repugnant vnto that obedience which wee owe vnto Gods Law, and ſo we offend our Lord and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. Thirdly, by the vnrighteouſneſſe of our actions we are defectiue in our Charitie, and thereby we offer wrong vnto our Brethren. And laſt of all, the peruerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and frowardneſſe of our wils doth trouble our hope and patience, and ſo we diſquiet our ſelues and the peace of our owne conſciences. Briefely, wee are hence to learne,<note place="margin">Math. 3.3.</note> that the Preaching of <hi>Iohn (who came to prepare the waies of the Lord, and to make his pathes ſtraight)</hi> doth in that place intimate thus much vnto vs, that all theſe foureirregularities, are to be rectified if we hope to haue the ſpirit of Chriſt to inhabite and poſſeſſe vs. And therefore theſe our affections muſt be wained from the things of this world, for <hi>we cannot ſerue two Maiſters</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour;)<note place="margin">Luk. 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>We cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> the pride of our hearts is to be abaſed; for <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace vnto the humble.</hi> Thirdly, the vnrlghteouſneſſe of our actions is to be rectified;<note place="margin">Mark. 4.24.</note> for <hi>With what meaſure we meite vnto others, the ſame will God meite vnto vs.</hi> And laſtly, the peruerſeneſſe of our wils is to be moderated;<note place="margin">Iames 1.20.</note> for <hi>the wrath of man cannot accompliſh the will of God,</hi> but a <hi>meeke and a quiet ſpirit is a thing before God much ſet by.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4.</note> In fine, this is the ſumme of all, that in aſmuch as whiles we are in the fleſh; that is, afore we are renewed by Repentance, the motions of ſinne, which are by the Law, doe preuaile in our members to bring forth fruit vnto death: ſo now when as grace doth appeare, and that the kingdome of God is at hand; all impediments are to be remoued, which might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the worke of the ſpirit of grace within vs: ſo that we may he euery way fitted; <hi>that we may be able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height; that we may be filled withall fulneſſe of God,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3, 18.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8333:7"/>
            <p> And the Baptiſt, doth not onely teach wherein Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance doth conſiſt, and what it muſt be; but hee alſo confirmes his Doctrine by his owne example, ſhewing how it muſt be practiſed of all true penitentiaries; and that eſpecially in their particulars. The place where he liued and Preached, and that was in the wilderneſſe. The meate whichhe ate, and that was locuſts and wilde ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. And laſtly, the garments which he wore, and that was a rough raiment of Camels haire, girt about his loynes with a leatherne girdle. In all which he ſignified vnto all men what he was, and what all true Repentants ſhould be; euen euery way mortified vnto this world; for <hi>All that is in this world</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>is the luſt of the fleſh, the iuſt of the eyes, or the pride of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.16.</note> The luſt of the fleſh he ſubdued, for he pampered not his body with varietie of delicacies, neither troubled hee his thoughts with prouiding the dainties of theſe times, but conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe with ſuch meane refreſhment as would one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but ſuſtaine nature, ſuch as that wilde deſart would afford, nothing but locuſts and wilde honey. The luſt of the eyes he preuented, for he dclighted not in the gariſh ſhewes and vaine ſpectacles of this world, neither deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he the ſocietie of good-companions and merrie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts, but ſequeſtred himſelfe into the wilde wilderneſſe, a deſart place, from all occaſions of ſinne, auoiding all allurements that might withdraw him, and all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that might prouoke him to froget the duetie of his vocation. And laſtly, the pride of this life he mortified; for thoſe ſoft and coſtly raiments whereby the pride of mans heart is aduanced and openly manifeſted vnto the world, did hee contemne, and apparelled himſelfe in ſuch a garment as befitted one whoſe profeſſion did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge himſelfe vnworthy of any, and therefore contented himſelfe in humilitie with the meaneſt, euen a rough coate of camels haire girt about his loynes with a leatherne belt.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:8333:8"/>
            <p> His practiſe is an example vnto vs; and that ſo plaine, that there are few (I am perſwaded) but doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, and can eaſily make application thereof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues: and therefore (the time calling me on) I will not further exemplifie things ſo manifeſt and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, as the neceſſitie and dueties of Repentance, which though practiſed ſincerely of few, yet the doctrine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is a high-way ſo much beaten and ſo plaine, that a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther guide were needeleſſe. Onely afore I proceede; of the ceremoniall part of <hi>Iohns</hi> Doctrine,<note place="margin">Hook Eccl. pol. lib. 5.</note> the outward admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacrament of Baptiſme, thus much: That the adminiſtration of the outward ſignes is occaſioned by the weakeneſſe of our faith and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which as they doe much depend vpon ſenſe, ſo muſt they haue ſome kinde of ſenſible obiect to conuey vnto the vnderſtanding what is to be beleeued. And therefore ſith God in himſelfe is inuiſible, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by vs be diſcerned working, therefore (I ſay) when it ſeemeth good in the eyes of his heauenly wiſedome that men for ſome ſpeciall intents and purpoſes ſhould take notice of his glorious preſence: he giues vnto vs ſome plaine and ſenſible tokens, whereby to know what we cannot ſee. So communicating by ſenſible meanes, thoſe bleſſings, that are incomprehenſible; aſſuring vs thereby in this particular, that as water doth waſh away the filth of the fleſh; ſo doth the blood of Chriſt cleanſe our ſoules from all pollution of ſinne, by repentance and faith in his name.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things being conſidered, what ſhould I hence inferre, but euen take vp the complaint of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> in the firſt verſe of his 53.<note place="margin">Eſay 53.1.</note> Chapter. <hi>Who will beleeue our report?</hi> when as there are ſo many profeſſours and ſo few practiſers of true and vnfained Repentance: Euery man almoſt (as <hi>Herod</hi>) harbouring in his breſt ſome minion ſinne or other, from whence he will not be diuorced; when as the vallyes of ſome are not raiſed, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8333:8"/>that their affections doe yet lie groueling vpon the earth, raking and rooting in the mire of this world, and latoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglecting the golden treaſures of heauen: The ſweſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling pride of others being ſuch, that they can thinke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily of none but themſelues: The iniquitie of others like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, baniſhing all truth and honeſty from their dealings: and laſtly, the boiſterous and outragious paſſions of ſome giuing aſſured teſtimony, that as yet their rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath not beene made ſmooth by the power of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Neither doth the outward face of mens carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and deportment giue other witneſſe, but that many think the example of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> doth nothing coeern them. For though there ought (I confeſſe) to be an orderly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of degrees by outward habits and other the needefull concernements of this life: Yet in theſe times it ſeemes mens mindes are vncapable of moderation, when as in euery ſucceſſion euery one for the moſt part deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to exceede him that went before him, both in diet, apparell, and other complements of Nature; <hi>As if there were no profit vnto a man</hi> (as the wiſe man ſpeakes) <hi>but that he eate, and drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>and delight his ſoule in the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this worlds vanitie.</hi> And that which is worſt of all, the vnteachableneſſe of many, giues ſtrong ſuſpition that their eſtate is wel-nigh deſperate, when as by the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reces wherwith the Church our Mother now trauaileth, (which ſhould humble vs) doe they take aduantage to harden their hearts the more For the one ſide (ſay they) are too licentious, the other too curious, and in the meane time they will bereformed by neither: much like thoſe wicked <hi>Phariſes</hi> of whom our Sauiour ſpeakes in the eleuenth of <hi>Mathew;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.18.19</note> for <hi>Iohn came neither eating nor drinking, and yet they ſaid he had a Diuell. The Sonne of man came eating and drinking, and they ſaid behold a glutton, a drinker of wine, and a friend vnto Publicans and ſinners.</hi> So that the truth is, that when mens mindes are ſo ſetled vpon the things of this world, that neither the threatnings of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8333:9"/>the law, nor the promiſes of the Goſpell, neither the reſtraints of the one, nor the liberties of the other, can preuaile to make men forſake their ſinnes, there is great preſumption that their God is their bellie, when as their vnbrideled appetite is their ſole religion. The exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the inuectiues, the exhortations of the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of God, from and againſt theſe courſes, are euery where ſo frequent, that its hopeleſſe, and therefore needeleſſe for me to multiply the ſame Onely thus much to conclude this point. Let vs all remember (beloued) what great account we haue to paſſe at that laſt Audite, when our chiefe fauourites, the fancie-feeding and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering pleaſures of this world ſhall all ſhrinke from vs, and nothing but our owne deedes and deſerts ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company vs before the iudgement ſeate of God.</p>
            <p>And ſo I paſſe briefely from the poſitiue Doctrine of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the nature of Repentance; to the other part thereof, its relatiue nature, the end of it, why it was, that is to ſay, <hi>That Chriſt might be made manifeſt vnto Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely it was the chiefeſt intendment of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt in this place, not to ſhew what, but wherefore his Miniſterie ſerued. For indeede of it ſelfe it was almoſt as nothing; it was but a bare beginning of that which was to be made perfect by another Miniſterie. For although at that time Chriſt was come into the world,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1</note> yet the world knew him not; yet though he came vnto his own, yet his owne receiued him not: becauſe the light ſhined in fuch darkneſſe as was not able to comprehend it So that of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity it was requiſite that there ſhould proceeds another Miniſterie whereby to clecre that glolmie darkeneſſe that ouer-ſhadowed mens mindes from apprehending the light.</p>
            <p>Our inſerence therfore from this place ſhal be that Chriſt could not be manifeſted vnto Iſracl, neither is it poſſible that we ſhould euer come to the true knowledg of Chriſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8333:9"/>without the Miniſterie of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> the preaching and practiſe of (at leaſt one degree of) Repentance going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, For the ſame reaſon which was affirmatiuly giuen of the abrogation of the old Sacrament which did prefigure this, that <hi>if yee be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall proſit you nothing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.2.</note> doth on the negatiue follow the inſtitution of this; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that if we be not baptiſed, aſſuredly Chriſt ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit vs nothing. And in ſaying ſo, I ſay no more then our bleſled Sauiour himſelfe ſaid vnto that great Doctor of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in the third of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell; <hi>Verely, verely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>I ſay vnto thee, except that a man be brone of water and of the Spirit, bee cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> For, there is a two-fold Baptiſme: the one, by the Ancients called <hi>Baptiſmus flaminis,</hi> the Baptiſme of water: the other, <hi>Baptiſmus flaminis,</hi> the Baptiſme of the Spirit and fire. The firſt is a preparation to the ſecond. And therefore ſaith the <hi>Baptiſt; I indeede baptize you with water to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>but hee that commeth after mee, is mightier then I, whoſe ſhooes I am not worthy to beare: he will baptize you with the holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that wee may further proue it neceſſary to the manifeſtation of Chriſt, the very Inſcription of <hi>Iohns</hi> miniſterie makes it euident,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>The voyce of a Cryer in the Wilderneſſe, prepare the way of the Lord, make his paths ſtraight.</hi> That as wee know it is an vſuall thing for Princes and great men, afore they come to any place, to haue their Harbingers to goe before them, to make euen their way, and to prepare a fit place to entertaine them againſt they come: So the Lord hauing ordayned the ſould of man to be his Temple, will firſt haue it ſwept and cleanſed by ſomewhat of repentance, from the filth and pollution of ſinne, afore he will make it his dwelling place. And it is very conſonant vnto reaſon: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For ſeeing vpon the comming of Chriſt wee are to make a new Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant with God, it is very vnfit it ſhould be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome kinde of preparation. For, looke but into the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8333:10"/>time of the giuing of the Law, and yee ſhall ſee how the people were to be prepared afore they were to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord to make a Couenant with him at the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of <hi>Sinai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.10.11</note> how they were to be ſanctified and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two dayes, and the third day to come before him. Now that was the Couenant of workes, and it was giuen by the mediation of a ſeruant, <hi>Moſes:</hi> but this is the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, a better Couenant, &amp; giuen by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him that is ſonne and heyre of all; and therefore if preparation were needfull in the former, much more in this. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, the Baptiſt was not a Miniſter of the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.9.</note> nor a Prophet of the old; <hi>Fuit tamen pluſquam Propheta,</hi> bee was more then a Prophet, and yet not ſo much as a Miniſter of the Goſpell: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
               <hi>the leaſt in the Kingdome of heauen</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour) <hi>is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then bee,</hi> as concerning the ſubiect of his Miniſterie: <hi>Furit autem terminus Legis,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
               <hi>&amp; initium Euangelij,</hi> Hee was the ending of the Law,<note place="margin">Marke 1.1.</note> and beginning of the Goſpell: and therefore Repentance (the chiefe ſubſtance of his Miniſterie) was to be preached betweene the Law and the Goſpell, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> inaſinuch as it hath reference vnto both. Thirdly, afore that time that Chriſt Ieſus by the glad tidings of the Goſpell, was made manifeſt vnto the world; and now alſo afore Chriſt be manifeſted vnto vs, both they then were, and wee now are ſubiect vnto the Law, and bound vnder a curſe to fulfill the ſame. But now <hi>foraſmuch as it was impoſſible vnto the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> 
               <hi>being of no ſtrength becauſe of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit alſo that dwelleth in vs luſting after enuie</hi> (as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>God ſending his owne Sonne to redeeme vs that were vnder the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.5.</note> can it ſtand with the Iuſtice of God, ſo to diſhonour his Law, as to receiue vs to mercy whiles we ſtill be contemners of it? No aſſuredly. But ſuch onely doth the Lord accept in Chriſt, as feeling themſelues vnable to fulfill the Law, doe for that cauſe ſubmit and proſtrate themſelues at the feete of Gods Iuſtice, with acknowledgement of their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8333:10"/>deſert, and with penitent and ſorrowfull hearts aske par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for their ſinnes. Not that the Lord requireth or accepteth repentance as meritorious, or in that kinde any way neceſſarie, for his mercy is onely ſufficient, but that a rebell cannot be receiued without ſubmiſſion. For the ſubiect of the Goſpell of Chriſt is a promulgation or a proclamation of pardon vnto all ſuch as indeed are rebels againſt God, but yet not if they continue ſo; but only vnto ſuch rebels as come in and ſubmit themſelues. It is cleare therefore and euident that the paths of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance lead and conduct vs vnto the Kingdome of Grace.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> For <hi>Come vnto me</hi> (ſaith our Lord Ieſus) <hi>all yee that are weary and heauy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> Now, can the Lord eaſe vs of ſinne, when we are already at ſo much eaſe that wee feele not our ſinnes; they trouble vs not? No, for the ſcope (I ſay) of Chriſtian do ctrine is the comfort of them whoſe hearts are ouer-charged with the burden of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if this will not ſuffice, let vs take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto the Ceremoniall Law, which was but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: for ſhadowes ſometimes may be better diſcerned then the ſubſtance it ſelfe, if the ſight be weake. As (for example) wee better diſcerne the forme of the Sunne by its ſhadow in the water, then in looking vpon its owne body, becauſe our ſight is weake.<note place="margin">Numb. 21.</note> So looke vpon the brazen Serpent, a figure and ſhadow of Chriſt, which had power giuen it to heale thoſe that felt themſelues bitten by the fiery Serpents, if they looked vp vnto the ſame: noting thereby thus much, that when the terrours of Gods iudgements for our ſinnes are ſo heauy vpon our ſoules, that they preſſe vs vnto the very death; if then by a liuely faith we can but looke vp vnto Chriſt, we ſhall be healed, our ſinnes ſhall be remitted: yet with this Prouiſo, this is alwayes to be preſuppoſed, that wee can neuer looke vp to be healed, vnleſſe firſt wee feele our ſelues wounded. And if wee want inſtances, take the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8333:11"/>Parable of the <hi>Seruant</hi> that fell downe at his Maſters feet,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.26.</note> deſiring patience and forbearance: and the Parable alſo of the <hi>Prodigall Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 15.20.</note> who hauing diſſolutely wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all his portion, returned home in great ſorrow and anguiſh of heart; and ſo thereby obtayned grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour againe. I will not ſtand any longer in amplifying and enlarging the proofe hereof, it being a thing that the tenour of Scripture doth alwayes import, and the practiſe of the Saints doth euery where confirme, that Chriſt cannot be truely manifeſted vnto vs, that is, his merits and mercy can neuer eyther be effectuall vnto vs, or rightly apprehended by vs, vnleſſe wee bee bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme; and waſhed with the water of Repentance.</p>
            <p>This therefore being ſo, if wee doe but reflect our thoughts from what wee ſhould be, vnto what wee are, and euery one examine his owne heart, what his eſtate is, and how many are there, that eyther will be aſſured, or ſhall greatly doubt that they haue as yet no clayme, no intereſt nor benefit at all by the merits of Chriſts death, becauſe they feele no alteration in themſelues from what they haue beene at the firſt, they haue neuer ſubmitted themſelues to the miniſterie of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt;</hi> they haue neuer truely and throughly repented them of their ſinnes; and therefore as yet Chriſt is not made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto them, howſoeuer they haue deluded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>But yet here is not all:<note place="margin">Reu. 2.24.</note> for there are <hi>profunda Satanae,</hi> whereof <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſpeakes in the ſecond of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> that ſame deepeneſſe of Sathan which euery man cannot diſcouer in himſelfe. For it were well, if being in a damnable eſtate, men might feele and know they were what they are; for then there might be better hope of amendment, and poſſibilitie of reconciliation with God. But it is not ſo: for there are deluſions, myſteries, miſts of iniquitie, whereby a man ſhall be ſo deceiued (if hee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8333:11"/>looke not very carefully and warily vnto himſelfe) in iudging of his ſpirituall eſtate: that many men queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and that to with a good opinion of themſelues ſlip ſodainly away, and deſcend vnto the deepe at vnawares. It is not then from our purpoſe ſomewhat to vnmaske the vizard of hypocriſie, and to diſcouer the ſubtile illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Sathan; that ſeeing the deceit and danger, wee may the better auoyd the ſame.</p>
            <p>The firſt illuſion therefore whereby Hypocrites are deceiued, is too much relying and truſting in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward formes of Gods ſeruice. For it is true, that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the doctrine and Baptiſme of <hi>Iohn</hi> to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. Yet what then? haue they not ſufficiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelues vnto it, when they haue beene bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? what need they then (thinke they) to make any further ſeruple of being in the fauour of God? Is not the ſacrament of Baptiſme that ſame <hi>Lauacrum Regenerationis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tit. 3.5.</note> that bath of Regeneration (as the Apoſtle cals it) whereby they are made members of the Church of God, ſealed for the Children of God; and ſo aſſared of the remiſſion of their ſinnes?</p>
            <p>To which I anſwere, that it is a remarkable ſigne and token of a man whoſe heart is not ſincere, to glory and pleaſe himſelfe in the outward performance of religſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ceremonies, neglecting in the meane time the true ſubſlance of Grace, and the feare of God. An example whereof wee haue in the lewes, who chiefely inſulted in the Cuſtomes and Rites of the Law, crying,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> when as the Lord witneſſeth, that hee had nothing to doe with their new Moones, and their Sacrifices, their hearts being ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate, and their liues ſo prophane as they were: for that that hee eſpeciall required of them, was to <hi>amend their wayes and their workes.</hi> So it is in like manner in this particular of Baptiſme, wherein wee are neuer to thinke it ſefe to preſume of Gods grace by bare coniecturall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8333:12"/>hopes, in eleuating the outward meanes of life, the meanes fayling that ſhould come betweene. For though the Sacraments and their manner of adminiſtration be Gods owne ordinances, yet notwithſtanding doe they include a ſubordination of meanes, without which wee cannot actually be brought to enioy what God doth ſecretly intend. So that to build onely vpon notionall conceits, and outward formalities of Gods ſeruice, as though they were of themſelues eyther acceptable to God, or any whit behoouefull to our good, vnleſſe wee keepe our ſelues in the wayes wherein hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vs to walke, is but a ſelfe-deceiuing vanitie. And therefore the outward forme and adminiſtration of this Sacrament of Baptiſme is ineffectuall and vnauaileable without repentance true and ſerious. For the bare forme of Baptiſme in it ſelfe is but a meere Ceremonie, and though after a ſort neceſſary, yet not abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to mans ſaluation, although the graces repreſented by it be indiſpenſable. For wee may be ſaued without Baptiſmall water, but not without Baptiſmall Grace: neyther doth euery one receiue the grace of God, that receiues the Sacrament of his grace. For howſoeuer God vſe the Sacrament as an inſtrument to giue and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs of theſe graces, ſo that none doe ordinarily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the grace of remiſſion of ſinnes, without the Sacrament of Baptiſme duely adminiſtred: yet is not remiſſion of ſinnes ſo tyed vnto it, that whoſoeuer hath the one, is neceſſarily made partaker of the other, but that thouſands receiue the outward ſigne, which neuer ſhall taſte of the fauour of God.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, that wee may better conceiue the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of theſe men, and may more perfectly apprehend the truth of this poynt, wee are to know that there is a viſible Church, that is, a communitie of men ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from others, and ſanctified through the profeſſion of that truth which God hath taught the world by his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8333:12"/>Sonne. And there is an inviſible Church, that body myſticall whereof Chriſt is only the head, that building vndiſcernable by mortall eyes, wherein CHRIST is the chieſe Corner-ſtone. In the viſible Church there are outward meanes, in the inviſible Church there are inward graces required as meanes to aſſure vs of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God.</p>
            <p>Now though hee can neuer be a member of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Church, which is not firſt a member of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet euery one that is a member of the viſible, is not a member of the inviſible; for,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>all are not Iſraell that are of Iſraell.</hi> That which makes vs members of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church are the outward viſible meanes of grace, and our ſubmiſſion thereunto, the preaching of the Word, the receiuing of the Sacraments, and the like. That which makes vs members of the inviſible Church are the inward graces of the Spirit, Repentance, Faith. Hope and Loue. <hi>Profeſſing</hi> the truth in the one. in the other <hi>obeying</hi> the truth is of neceſſitie required. Now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto theſe, our iudgement of our ſelues and others ought to be after a different manner: of others, Charitie muſt direct vs: of our ſelues, Faith muſt aſſure vs. If wee ſee others ſubmit themſelues to the outward ordinarie meanes of life, the rule of Charitie that hopeth all things, is that wee hope well of all men; and therefore that thoſe that we ſee are outwardly baptiſed, wee iudge as inwardly regenerated, becauſe our iudgement of others can extend no further then the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: But if wee haue no other aſſurance of our owne ſafetie but by outward meanes, our hopes are but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. For, that which wee hope of others, wee muſt feele in our ſelues; wee muſt feele that inward grace within vs, which makes the outward meanes effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall vnto vs: and therefore if wee feele not Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in our ſelues, our Baptiſme is ineffectuall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auaileable.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8333:13"/>
            <p> Againe in the ſecond place, although men of diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and ſcandalous carriage, may by enidence of reaſon be brought to confeſſe, that their outward Bpatiſme is vnauaileable without inward and true Repentance: yet doth the Diuell, through their owne corruption, ſo farre preuaile with them, as to perſwade them, and make them thinke that they repent, when as indeede they doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe. For whereas Repentance doth eſpecially conſiſt in a dying to ſinne:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>how ſhall they that are dead to ſinne</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>yet liue therein? If therefore we ſay that</hi> (by dying to ſinne) <hi>we haue fellowſhip with Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>and yet walke in darkeneſſe, we lie and doe not truely,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> And yet for all this, ſuch is the miſterie of imquitie that by the ſubtiltie of Satan and the falſeneſſe of mens owne hearts, they ſtill thinke they doe repent, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede they repent not. For there may be ſome generall diſpoſitions vnto Repentance euen in Hypocrites; as a willing ſubmiſſion vnto the outward means of life, a deſire of Saluation, a kinde of hate, of griefe, and ſorrow for ſome ſinnes, ſome kinde of obedience alſo vnto many of Gods commandements, which may giue them ſome cauſe to thinke that the ſpirit of God workes in them the grace of repentance; when as in truth it is nothing ſo, becauſe there is euerſome great defect therein which makes it imporfect, and ſo vnacceptable, either it is not ſincere, or not entire, or built vpon ſome indirect and oblique reſpect or other. As firſt for example in the <hi>Phariſes</hi> that came to <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme, there was queſtionleſſe ſome doubt made them in ſome ſort think well of themſelues, but yet it was not ſincere,<note place="margin">Math. 3.7.</note> as it appeares by <hi>Iohns reproofe.</hi> So alſo it is ſaid of <hi>Horod,</hi> that he heard <hi>Iohn</hi> gladly, which quieted his couſcience in ſome degree, vet it was but for a time; it continued not. Againe, in <hi>Balaaem,</hi> there was both a feare of euill. and a deſire of good, he was very loath, vnwilling and fearefull to curſe the children of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8333:13"/>
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he alſo deſired from his heart he might die as the righteous: but yet theſe affections in him were not true, they proceeded from a ſeruile, baſe, deiected minde, onely <hi>formidene poenae,</hi> for feare of the danger hee ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre if he did otherwiſe. So likewiſe in <hi>Saul</hi> there was ſome kinde of obedience to Gods commandements; yet was not his obedience entire; for being commanded to deſtroy all and ſpare nothing of <hi>Amelecke,</hi> which for the moſt part he did; yet he reſerued <hi>Agag</hi> and ſome few of the beſt things, pretending to offer them in ſacrifice vnto the Lord at his returne, contrary to his commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: ſo that though a wicked impenitent man may obay God in much, ye there is alwaies ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he loues better then Gods Commandement, and that alſo muſt be cloaked ouer with religions pretence. And laſtly, <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> vpon whoſe affections the doctrine of Repentance tooke ſuch impreſſion that it made them ſell their poſſeſſions and all they had, &amp; lay downe the price at the Apoſtles feete, onely they kept backe ſome ſmall part thereof to helpe them if occaſion ſhould ſerue, which one would haue thought would not haue beene cenſured with ſuch a heauie iudgement as it was: for its euer the propertie of an Hypocrite to guie ſome, but not all, when as God requires all, or none at all. Now ſuch is the courſe of many in theſe times, when as happily the Preaching of the word of God hath ſo ſtung them, that they muſt needes ſubmit and yeelde: they haue forſaken much of their former vanities and finfull practiſes; yet their deareſt beloued, their darling Sinne they reſerue, that muſt needes be diſpenſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: either couetouſneſſe, or pride, reuenge, or ſome ſuch other, and that to masked ouer with ſome plauſible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or other, as frugalitie, hanſomeneſſe, iuſtice, and the like; ſo wilie are men in this age to beguile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>But then it may be demaunded that if theſe motions
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8333:14"/>towards Repentance (though but in part) be of God, then are they good: if they be not of God, from whence doe they proceede? For anſwere whereunto we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that there are three principall actiue faculties in the ſoule of man, the vnderſtanding, the will, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; the vnderſtanding to direct, the will to obey; and the conſcience a faithfull and indifferent arbitratour betweene God and man, conerning both. Now the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding being inlightned, partly by the grounds of nature, partly by the word of God, of dueties to be done, of euils to be auoided; if the will doe obey, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth continually cheere and comfort vs in what eſtate or miſerie ſoeuer we are: But if the will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and will not ſubmit and obey; then is the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as a continuall torment euer accuſing and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs of high treaſon againſt God, and therefore when as our will is not nor cannot be brought vnto a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, we are of neceſſitie forced to counterfeit and delude the conſcience with ſome kinde of degrees of deuotion and outward ſeruices, euen to ſtill thoſe cries which if they were not ſtaied, were little better then a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entrance into hell. So that for the moſt part thoſe ſame vſuall and common ſighes and fained groanes which many men would faine make themſelues beleeue are ſignes and tokens of Repentance, are but the vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and exprobrations of conſcience which doe then accuſe them, and thoſe ſame flaſhes of light and hope which from the ſame they conceiue vnto themſelues of the loue and fauour of God,<note place="margin">1 King. 22.</note> are but the ſuggeſtions of that falſe ſpirit which was in the mouth of <hi>Ahabs</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that by their lying and falſe incouragement they may be hardned in their ſinnes, that ſo their fall might be the greater.</p>
            <p>A third deceit whereby men flatter themſelues, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is a conceit, or rather a miſconceit of their faith, attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo much vnto it, that they thinke there is ſcarce any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8333:14"/>thing elſe abſolutely and neceſſarily required of them; and that becauſe by it alone they are ioyned to Chriſt, nothing can diſioyne them; and therefore that the ſtrict exaction of ſo ſeuere a courſe of repentance is needeleſſe. Wherein they diſcouer their vaine ignorance that though they thinke they ſee, yet are they ſtill groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the darke, and are going they know not well which way. For without Repentance their faith is falſe and vaine. For we muſt know that there are three ſeuerall acts or degrees required to the perfection of faith, according to which it is diſtinguiſhed to be three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: either <hi>fides apprehenſionis,</hi> or <hi>fides approbationis,</hi> or <hi>fides applicationis,</hi> the one being the act of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the other of the will, and the laſt of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. The firſt apprehends the promiſes of God as true, the ſecond approues them as good, and the third applies them vnto our ſelues in particular, aſſuring vs they doe belong vnto vs. All theſe ſeuerall dueties and degrees are required vnto the compleate eſſence of faith. And as the laſt cannot be where the two former firſt are notſo the two firſt without it are fruitleſſe and imperfect. Now the two firſt degrees of faith, namely, to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the promiſes of God to be true, and approue them as good, may be in a man without repentance: But neither of theſe are that true ſauing euangelicall faith, which can aſſure vs that the benefits of Chriſts merits doe belong vnto vs in particular. Theſe are onely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall motiues vnto all kinde of good actions; theſe are that generall beliefe which is required by the Law of nature of euery man, as well heathen as Chriſtian, for the preſeruation of a good conſcience in all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoeuer, as well legall as euangelicall. To illuſtrate this by an example. Suppoſe this to be the propoſition. <hi>Hee that confeſſeth his ſinnes, and forſaketh them, ſhall finde mercie. Pro.</hi> 28.13. Where the promiſe of mercie is made vnto repentant ſinners: Now the firſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8333:15"/>act of faith in reference therunto, is by the vnderſtanding to apprehend it as true;<note place="margin">Iames 2.20.</note> but this faith is not perfect nor ſauing, for the diuels haue it; <hi>the diuels beleeue and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iames.</hi>) The ſecond degree of faith is by the will to approue and like it as good; and yet is this neither that true ſauing faith, for it was in <hi>Balaam, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, Agrippa,</hi> and it is in euery carnall profeſſour, none excepted.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> Neither of theſe therefore, nor both of theſe are of any force or validitie to confirme the promiſe of mercie vnto our owneſoules in particular; which is the chiefeſt propertie of faith. And yet thoſe are all that faith which is in any Chriſtian man afore repentance, and the chiefe motiue by which the ſpirit of God doth ſtirre vp the heart of man vnto repentance. Now after repentance, at leaſt the beginning thereof, followes the third act of faith by the conſcience, that applies the promiſe vnto our ſelues, and ſo our faith is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as Saint <hi>lame;</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>He that repenteth of his ſinnes,</hi> (ſaith the holy Ghoſt) <hi>ſhall ſinde mercie,</hi> thats the Theſis: Now after repentance the conſcience makes the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>but I haue repented of my ſinnes;</hi> and then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion directly followeth, that <hi>therefore the promiſe of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie belongs vnto me.</hi> This then is that true, liuely, and ſauing faith that aſſures vs of the grace of God; this is that faith whereby the ſpirit beares witneſſe with our ſpirits that wee are the adoped ſonnes of God. Yet would I not be thought to inferre hereby that there are in a Chriſtian three kindes, but onely three degrees of faith. For although that both the apprehending, and approu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, as they are in diuels and wicked men are things different from a true ſauing faith: yet in a regenerate man they are not diſtinct faiths, they doe not <hi>differreſpecie,</hi> they are not of different kines; but onely in reference vnto a true and perfect faith are as <hi>diſpoſuiones in ordine ad habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> as diſpoſitions towards a habite; or as <hi>media ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiaad finem,</hi> as meanes tending vnto the end of their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8333:15"/>perfection. Differing from the ſauing faith no otherwiſe then the power of vegetation and ſenſe, being diſtinct eſſences in other creatures, doe from the reaſonable ſoule, vnto which they onely are as ſubordinate faculties in man. There growes many difficulties, and much confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the vnderſtanding of the ſacred miſteries of our ſaluation, for want both of obſeruation of the order of the working of grace within vs, and alſo of diſtinct ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication what kinde or degree of grace the ſeuerall merits of Chriſt doe procure vs. To conclude this point therefore, as the children of nature walke in darkeneſſe and confuſion: ſo the children of grace ſhould walke in light and diſtinction; and not onely talke wildely and confuſedly of their faith in Chriſt, of their hope, and other their great vertues, but alſo be able to diſcerne of the manner and order of the working of Gods ſpirit within them, and diſtinguiſh of the ſeuerall changings of their affections, and not that onely, but alſo feele the power thereof in their owne ſoules; and then ſhall they know whether they can certainely beleeue that their ſinnes are forgiuen afore they be repented of.</p>
            <p>Fourthly (for the hypocriticall heart of man hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny windings) it may be conceited (as it is by ſome) that they haue already repented, that time is already paſt. For there are ſome Anabaptiſticall and fanaticke ſpirits, that haue limited a certaine time for ſorrow and repentance, that imagine and affirme that men are to continue and lie vnder the terrours of conſcience euen vntill they be ready to vndertake ſome deſperate attempt, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fter they haue once eſcaped that danger, they thinke they are ſafe; they are ſo throughly ſeaſoned that euer after they remaine ſecure, all their droſſe is purged out; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on continually afterwards in a courſe of obſeruing and cenſuring other mens imperfections, and in the meane time neglect themſelues altogether. Whereas certaine it is that ſo long as we liue in this world, we ſhall ſhew our ſelues, euery one of vs to be but men full of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8333:16"/>frailtie and inſtabilitie, and therefore that our repentance is daily to be renewed. For as the naturall life of man doth conſiſt vpon that which is called by the Phyſitians <hi>humor radicalis,</hi> and <hi>calor naturalis,</hi> naturall heate and radicall moiſture (for indeede all life is ſuſtained by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and motion is betweene contrarieties:) ſo in our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life, there muſt of neceſſitie be two contrary qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, repentance continually to put off our own vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and faith to put on Chriſts righteouſneſſe, the one to worke vpon the other, ſo to preſerue life by mofect of good within vs, muſt repentance and faith be encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which muſt be vnto the end of our liues, for death onely is the end and complement of our repentance and mortification; euen as our reſurrection ſhall be the end and complement of our faith and viuification.</p>
            <p>Now the laſt ſhift (worth the ſpeaking of) which men frame vnto themſelues, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> thereby to ſlippe the bridle of mortification, is one vnworthy any man that is euen but of meane capacitie in vnderſtanding the ſacred miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his ſaluation, and vnworthy alſo either the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, or ſo much as mentioning were it not ſo common as it is, indeede being fitter to ſcare crowes then Chriſlians. And it is this, that in aſmuch as repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is ſo harſh vnto fleſh and blood, and practiſed of ſo few, and that the auerſe nature of man can hardly be drawne to vndergoe the ſame, that therefore the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable &amp; neceſſary exaction therof is a doctrine which might bring men to deſpaire, and ſo exceeding dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be vrged; wherein it is ſtrange to ſee that men ſhould be ſo ſtrongly deuoted to their owne diſtruction that they ſhould not acknowledge the meanes of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: but the Propheſie of the Apoſtle is fulfilled herein, where he foreſheweth that <hi>the time ſhould come when men would not ſuffer wholeſome doctrine,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> but hauing eares itching ſhall get themſelues teachers after their owne luſts.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:8333:16"/>But to returne and ſatisfie this great doubt. What needes any man to feare deſpaire?<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>The foundation of God remaineth ſure</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and hath this ſeale, The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 21.18.</note> and <hi>there ſhall not one hayre of their heads periſh.</hi> How then? ſhall the ordinance of God diſanull and ouerthrow the purpoſe of God? Indeed if any man ſhould goe about to deceiue and ouercharge ſimple ſoules by a deniall or extenuation of Gods mercy. inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating that it were eyther hopeleſſe or a hazard to truſt vnto the ſame: it were dangerous and like enough to ſwallow them vp with diſtraction or diſpaire; but ſo long as Repentance is but taught truely for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and that remiſſion of ſinnes is not obtayned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it: Let <hi>Paul</hi> plant, and <hi>Apollos</hi> water, let euery man doe his duety and performe his charge, and referre the euent and ſucceſſe to him that is able to diſpoſe of all things to his owne glory,<note place="margin">Fpheſ. 1.11.</note> and <hi>worketh all things after the counſell of his owne will:</hi> And then let what will fall out, it is our part to giue praiſe vnto God thereby; knowing this,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.15.16.</note> that the Goſpell as it is ordayned the ſauour of life vnto life vnto ſuch as ſhall be ſaued, euen ſo by Gods owne purpoſe is it the ſauour of death vnto death vnto thoſe that ſhall be damned.</p>
            <p>And therefore this ſcruple is but a cracke that doth more feare then hurt, diſcouering both folly in the heads and prophaneſſe in the hearts of thoſe that obiect the ſame. For it is certaine, that when mens affections are ſo ſtrongly ſet vpon vanitie, that by no meanes they will be drawne from the ſame: they inuent and imagine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually how to oppoſe, and diſable the force of that which they thinke doth any way checke or reſtraine their vnbridled luſts: and ſo eſpecially ayme to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue and gaine-ſay the neceſſitie of repentance and mortification, by ſuch friuolous and ridiculous argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as theſe: and yet as they thinke wiſely to. For of this ſort ſome there are that are in their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8333:17"/>of ſo refined and ſublimated temper, that they thinke they are too wiſe, and account it as a diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their high ſpirits, to ſubmit themſelues to the fooliſhneſſe of God (for, <hi>the preaching of the Croſſe of Chriſt is to them that periſh fooliſhneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.18.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle) and therfore doe they alwayes (as much as in them lyes) diſcountenance and diſharten any that are of ſtricter and more conſcionable carriage then themſelues. Others of them there are alſo ſo farre from imbracing repentance, that they oppoſe by all meanes againſt it, and like iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Iſmaels</hi> ſet themſelues to ſcorne and diride the ſame; ſo that whoſoeuer vndertaketh that holy courſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelfe to all the cenſure and obloquie that ſuch wicked and prophane hearts can inuent. Yea, to ſo ſtrange a height of Atheiſme are men growne in theſe times, that ordinarily they deeme and tearme others cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and preciſe, not becauſe they are buſie Polyprag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, hauing an Oare in euery mans Boat, and iudging of euery mans conſcience; neyther for their affected ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie and nice curioſitie; nor for that bold and blinde zeale of <hi>Vzza,</hi> in medling with that which belongs onely vnto the Prieſts office; nor yet for their rebellious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Church-gouernment and Gouernours; all which might giue iuſt occaſion to ſuſpect hypocriſie in any one: but onely for this cauſe, becauſe they were not eyther ſo monſtrous blaſphemers, or ſo great carou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, at leaſtwiſe ſo careleſſe and diſſolute liuers as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. But leauing ſuch monſters of Nature to the mercy of him who is onely able to transforme and amend them, let it neuer be heard amongſt vs (beloued) that any true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vertuous and Chriſtianly diſpoſed minde ſhould euer ſo much as once open his mouth to gaine-ſay that which Chriſt hath ſpoken,<note place="margin">Luke 13.3.5.</note> that if <hi>wee repent not, we ſhall all ſurely periſh.</hi> The leaſt ſinne, eyther in thought, word or deed, is death without repentance. Let not therefore the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our owne hearts delude vs, nor the feare of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8333:17"/>diſcourage vs, nor the imputation of mopiſh Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, which the world caſts vpon Repentance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold vs from vndertaking the ſame: for it is the Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the King of Heauen: it is the beginning of the Goſpell of Chriſt: it is an entrance into thoſe heauenly &amp; ſpirituall ioyes, wherewith the Saints vpon the earth are endued, being ſuch as the world can neyther giue vnto vs, nor take away from vs. For there is neuer any heart more filled with the ioyes of the Spirit, then that heart that hath taken the greateſt ſorrow for his ſinnes. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the portion of Grace giuen vnto any by a greater meaſure then vnto him in whom there is the greateſt meaſure of repentance.</p>
            <p>And though the naturall man (that perceiues not the things of God) thinkes it a Paradoxe that a Chriſtian ſhould reioyce in mourning: yet the Holy Ghoſt hath recorded it by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> as a conſolation for the Saints of God vnto the end of the world,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.6.8.</note> that <hi>though for a ſeaſon they be in heauineſſe (if need require) through manifold ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, yet doe theſe beleeue and reioyce with ioyes vnfpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and glorious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Humble your ſelues therefore</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>) <hi>vnder the mighty hand of God, that hee may exalt you in due time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 4.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Sorrow yee and weepe</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iames</hi>) <hi>let your laughter be turned into mourning; and your ioy into heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Caſt downe your ſelues before the Lord, and hee will lift you vp.</hi> Elſe will hee (ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi>)<note place="margin">Iob 40.5.</note> 
               <hi>who ſitteth in the heauens decked with maieſtie and excellencie, and arrayed with beauty and glory, caſt abroad the indignation of his wrath, and behold euery one that is proud, and abaſe him, and looke on euery one that is arrogant, and bring him low.</hi> And for concluſion of all, let euery man liuing, yea, euen the greateſt deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, remember, that it is an euerlaſting truth regiſtred in the ſacred Booke of God, <hi>Whereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>the heauens and earth ſhall paſſe afore one iot or tittle ſhall fall away,</hi> That,<note place="margin">Amos 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>woe is vnto them that are at eaſe in Sion:</hi> and,<note place="margin">Luke 6.25.</note> 
               <hi>woe vnto them that now laugh, for they ſhall weepe:</hi> And on the contrary, <hi>They
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8333:18"/>that ſow in teares ſhall reape in ioy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.5. Mat. 5.4.</note> and <hi>bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi> Now the Lord for his infinite mercy ſake, ſo preuaile in vs and ouer-rule vs by the power of his holy Spirit, that in the due and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration of our owne miſerie by ſinne, wee may ſo partake with him in his ſorrowes and ſufferings in this life, that wee may hereafter be made partakers with him of thoſe vnſpeakable and euerlaſting ioyes in the life to come, which hee reſerueth in the Kingdome of heauen, for all thoſe onely, that long and waite for his apearing. Which the Lord grant vnto vs for Chirſt his ſake: vnto whom with the Father, and his moſt bleſſed Spirit, bee all glory and maieſtie, all prayſe and thankſgiuing, both now and for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8333:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
